so um thanks everybody for um coming along to
uh another magnet and it's been great to see
another good turnout of people we will
um just a reminder for him who hasn't um
come along to one of these seminars um we have
presentations that are about uh 30 minutes or so
in in length uh we kindly ask that you keep your
microphones muted um during the presentation
so it's not to interrupt the speaker and if
you're struggling with um internet performance
or connection um if you turn off uh your video
uh that can help to improve the the connection
um at the end of the uh the seminar we'll have
time for a 10-15 minute um discussion and um
we'll invite you to to raise your hands and unmute
and to ask your questions but if you don't want to
to to ask a question in person by all means just
type it into to the chat and either myself or
one of the other conveners uh we'll read them out
for you and as always life is going on around us
in the background so if you have to to get up and
go and just uh get up and go and at the end of of
the seminars will have time for a bit of a catch
up uh but if a social which um is is not recorded
and so today um i'm really pleased to to to say
that we have uh lesnar from scripps institute of
oceanography and he will not be talking about
the application of the uh sunakawa shaw method
that's uh a copy-paste error from last week
um les will be talking about uh micromagnetism
and understanding the energy barriers that dictate
the stability of paleomagnetic grains so i'll
hand over to les he'll be able to give us his his
proper title okay um i'll quickly share my screen
so i'm assuming that everybody can see this
uh yes we can yeah okay fantastic all right
yeah so um i just want to thank greg and
um all the uh organizers for um asked me to
give this um presentation um and i'm just gonna
talk a bit about uh micromagnetic modeling
of size and thermal stability and really
what i want to expand upon is how we can
use micromagnetic modeling and computational
techniques to really try and get a grip on
some of the big questions in paleomagnetism
okay so so we know that uh paleomagnetism is one
of the few uh if not only uh geophysical methods
that really is paleo and uh we find it astonishing
that we can uh fight rocks that record events that
happened uh billions of years ago uh but the
existing uh theory that underpins paleomagnetism
is is currently quite old and it does
struggle to explain the next generation
of paleomagnetic problem and uh so
the images that you see here are some
images of technique that can be used to
directly um image the domain structures
that we see in the tiny magnetic grains
that we see in our pelletic samples
and the image that you see here on the
left is just a simple uniform domain but
the one on the right here is much more
complicated it's non-uniform but it's
all summary that we have is blind to how these
non-uniform brains behave um so before we examine
how we put together a more complete theoretical
understanding let's just take a quick overview
of some of the big impacts of the paleomagnetic
record phenomenon um so what do natural recorders
tell us well uh as we know um then natural
recorders can tell us about the evolution of
our planet's field they give us an indication
of yes how the escort formed and uh they give
us information about its current behavior and on
the surface of the earth we see that the magnetic
field isn't just a simple north-south dipole as
this map of the earth's field intensity shows
where do features such as the south atlantic
normally this big blue spot in the image come
from is it transient is it primordial we know
that changes in the field should be visible in the
paleomagnetic record but if we don't understand
the recording process how do we know that we're
reconstructing the field correctly and beyond
earth the paleomagnetism allows us to understand
the recording phenomena in solar planetesimals for
example we think that the moon once had an active
geodynamo but what are lunar samples actually
recording are the recording thermal magnetization
chemical remnancies or impacts recovering the
paleo intensity we know is particularly hard
but understanding it is vital to our models
but finally the recording phenomena tells
us something about how our societies evolved
uh archaea magnetism can be
used today at historical sites
and understand their usage as you can
see it's hot burning experiment and
even being a recent science paper it's quite
controversial it suggested that a paleomagnetic
event delachamp excursion was responsible
for the extinction of the neanderthals
so controversial findings like these rest
on our understanding of natural recorders
which are the foundation of the paleo magnetic
record so in a nutshell we're trying to understand
um what the earth's field tells us about planetary
processes uh we know that the field is recorded in
rocks and so in principle we're just to go away
dig up some samples and take measurements right
well unfortunately it's not that
easy because since forming a rock
has undergone all kinds of alteration chemical
physical and understanding how the recording
have these recorded signals change over time
uh allows us to reconstruct the original field
uh so i just want to give a brief outline of
what we're going to be looking at so first i just
want to take a brief um aside and really think
about what i mean by signal recording and domain
structure and um we'll also take a quick look at
realistic main structures using micromagnetics
next we'll take a look at an example
of what happens to the domain structure
of a grain as it grows and shrinks again
and finally i'll take a quick examination of
uh thermal stability of magnetic
recording for more realistic grains
so the term signal are recording and domain
they kind of closely related to each other
to the point where i tend to use them um
interchangeably um but what you're looking
at here in the picture is a 100 nanometer grain of
magnetite with some non-uniform domain structure
and a sample is going to consist of thousands
of these small grains and the next sum of the
magnetic field caused by these grains is what
you're going to measure in a magnetometer
so in a sense these domain structures um are
the signal um now for a grain we can just
plot some arrows and visualize what's
going on but it's not very clear
this picture here that you see is quite busy we
can't really see the structures inside the grain
so for example the vortex nature of the
structure here is quite difficult to discern
so to bring out the structure we can color
these arrows um by using various quantities
so the quality here is something we call helicity
and you can think of this as a way of measuring
the local twisting of the field so if you imagine
pointing your thumb along the vortex core so these
will be the sort of the red arrows pointing out
and your fingers will be kind of twisting around
this represents a right-handed port
i also use these iso surfaces here
um to reduce the complexity of the structure to
its essence um and that's what your um and that's
something that allows us really to peer inside
the grain and reduce these comp complex structures
uh we can also calculate other quantities uh
to help us visualize the domain structures uh
now one of these is um something we called an
anisotropic direction of moments or adm and it's
really just telling us uh how far the magnetic
moments are from one of the crystal and easy axes
uh suffer magnetite uh this colouring scheme is
going to be blue for anything along the easy axis
which is something pointing along a cubic
diagonal and uh for anything that's red
that's going to be a vector pointing
along the hard axis of a cube edge
and we can get most of here with these
things we can take slices through the planes
through the grains um to get an idea of what's
going on in the internal structure so one of
the things that we see um are the reason why
these vortex cores plot as three red spots when
we use the um the adm or the direction of moments
what we're really seeing are the magnetic moments
kind of rotating through 360 degrees so
they're going to sweep out the three easy
directions which you see blue so these are the
three easy directions and then the three three
which correspond to the spots
and that's the vortex core
um and so we spent some time looking at a
single grain um and how it can be visualized
is to put rock uh we know it's an assemblage
of these grains and we can break that uh grain
up into its constituent parts uh then
we can calculate the behavior of each
grain using micromagnetics and finally we can
reconstruct the behavior of realistic samples
so that's the that's the kind of the big
picture idea of what we're trying to achieve
so when we do micromagnetic calculations uh
what we find is that there's a real divergence
in domain structure from what the
existing theories are based on
most theories rely on a single
domain or uniform field assumption
but as grains increase in size and as you can
see in these pictures here the domain structures
available become much more complex so what
you're seeing here is a cube of magnetite
and an example of some of the domain
structures that are available to it
as we increase in size so we go from a classic
uniform to a boat shape we call this the flower
domain state to something that's a vortex and
then to other much more complicated domain states
so just a quick recap we want to be able to
reconstruct planetary fields in the past and
we know that these fields are locked away
in paleomagnetic particles in rocks or in
the magnetic particles in rocks but recovering the
field is difficult and we need a fuller picture of
how you can do this using micromagnetics and we
can reduce the complexity of our micromagnetic
models by calculating some useful quantities
like helicity and adm that i've just described
so one of the things that we're interested in is
how stable domain structures are as a function of
the grain size so we could think of this as a kind
of an analog to some kind of chemical alterations
so why don't we take a look at
what happens as a grain grows
and the images you see here along the bottom show
progression from single domain through to single
vortex through to something truly multi-domain and
the question really here is how do we get there
uh in a recent study we examined this process
from a grade from about 200 nanometers up to
about three microns and the procedure is to take
a starting demand state and then gradually grow
the grain geometry calculating the
magnetic structures along the way
so let's take a journey to see how the domain
structure evolves as a function of grain size
and hopefully we can fill in this last picture in
the sequence with something a bit more realistic
so when we begin at 200 nanometers um i've
plotted here the illicit the iso surfaces
in three directions on the top uh with the
direction of moments of this adm quantity
taken from two slice planes through the grain
at the bottom so one of them is through a
grain that's perpendicular to the one one one
direction or a cubic diagonal and the other one
uh so this is the cubic diagonal one here on
the bottom left at bottom right sorry and the
uh this is just an into some intermediate play
just to give you an idea of what's happening
and as we do that um we see that the vortex
call becomes a little bit more developed
but nothing too exciting is happening we can
keep increasing the size further and further
and further still we start to see some interesting
features forming so notice that there's a kind
of ridge forming here along the tube um and it's
kind of beginning to resemble something more like
a twisted triangle you can really see the kind of
more triangular structure in this image on the top
right uh you can also see the spots in the slice
image begin to elongate and look more like ovals
so let's continue but we can see that that
ridge begins to develop a little bit more
and at this point the exit ends of the
twisted triangle begin to form these fins
and you can really see the triangular
this kind of twisted triangular nature now
in the iso surface and if we look at the slices we
can see that these blue regions um are beginning
to form something so let's continue to increase
the size um at this point uh the ends of the ice
solar-like structure so they're
kind of growing out from the center
of the of the vortex and you can really see
the beginning of the formation of domains in
the slices that's these blue regions here
they're becoming very much more developed
if we continue to grow the grain uh so now
we're up to uh one point um 1.2 microns quite
big now um we um we see that these propeller this
kind of propeller structure really looks uh very
apparent and the domain structures begin to look
much more distinct on the on the bottom images
um and finally we we see the elements
of of these small caps at about 1.5
microns microns on the edges here and uh we
really begin to see the formation of domain walls
in the bottom images and these caps then finally
join with the main body so you've got these uh
kind of close your domains forming in so you can
kind of see these here in the bottom images you've
got these nice big distinct domains um forming and
finally the maximum size i was able to model we
see very distinct uh multi-dimensional structure
in the slices the iso surface is now very complex
but the spaces correspond to the domains that
we see in the slices so these spaces here
so the domains are colored blue and this is what
we would expect because blue if you recall from
the direction of moments corresponds to a vector
in the easy direction and so we would expect um
the magnetization in the domain region to be
pointing along the easy direction and or long
magnetic crystalline easy axes and this is indeed
the case and if we take this point and we start to
decrease the size so we start to shrink the
grain um we find that the domain structure is um
it's actually quite stable um and it
persists um we'll just keep reducing the size
so i'm just slowly cycle through the reduction of
the size um we see that at about 1.2 microns there
are still fairly distinct and clear domains and
if you recall from the slide that corresponds to
this as we were growing the domain walls they were
much more fuzzier and much uh less well-formed at
this size uh maybe i'll go back to that there
so you see these they're much more fuzzier
and here they're much more distinct so clearly
there's um uh there's a there's a size hysteresis
there um and reducing the size even further
we see that the complicated domain structure
begins to disappear the size of the grain it's
not big enough to support this domain it's big
domain structure anymore so it's beginning to
disappear and then we just keep reducing the size
until we get back to our back to our nice vortex
core and then finally um we're at a slightly
smaller size and we see that the vortex structure
persists and so what does this mean well this
means that there's definitely a scientists exist
in the observed structures and we uh we can also
see um that there's multi-domain structures
these multi-domain structures seem to form
as outgrowths from the core towards the air i can
also see that the domains themselves uh contain
moments pointing along the magneto crystal and
easy axes which is this is what we would expect
and finally uh we can complete our sequence with
a more realistic picture of a multi-domain grain
and if we look in a lot more detail
um at the largest grain so this was
the main structure at the largest size we find
that the domain will width estimates and the
angles are between adjacent domains they compare
really quite well with theoretical calculations
so we see that in some circumstances
the magnetic single um can remain
even though the grain is undergoing
quite um quite large changes in size
so what about the thermal behavior uh well we can
also look at thermal stability using our models
and we know that thermally acquired a remnant
magnetization of trm is a really important
mechanism of signal acquisition and the basic idea
is that a magnetic material cools from above the
curian field tools the ambient field is recorded
in the domain structure but as we know lots of
things happen to the grain before we get to
measure them so how thermally stable are they
oh so let's just take a quick recap of some
important ideas when we're considering trms
the curie temperature so this is a temperature
above which there is no magnetic structure
because the moments are just governed by thermal
noise and you can see this represented by the top
picture here and super paramagnetism uh there is a
domain structure but it's ch came all the possible
states to record anything for long enough uh
the relaxation time is uh the measurement of
the amount of time that it takes to jump from
one domain structure to another dimension and
the blocking temperature is a temperature at
which the grain ceases to be super paramagnetic
so we usually pick uh some lab length time like a
100 seconds or a thousand seconds to define this
time length and finally an lem state or a local
energy minimum state is the most energetically
favorable donate structure so everything that
we've been looking at so far have been lem states
and in the lab uh we recover a signal by
progressive key sample in the presence of
a known field uh this is called a partial trm or
ptrm and the lab experiment works on the principle
of risk of porosity independence and additivity
so these are called retalia laws um but these
laws are frequently violated in the laboratory we
can see this in in the lab the first image here
the first graph shows that single domain theory
predicts that the trm acquired versus the remnants
uh that remains ought to be linear but as these
experimental results show this is not the case
and in the second image we see that single demand
theory again gives us an indication that the
blocking temperature should be very distinct and
quite sharp but again the experimental results
don't behave this way and so the big question
is what is the cause of this non-linearity
of these so-called ptrm tails um in order to
understand the thermal stability we need to know
all the possible domain states that a grain can
support and the way that we do this is we just
generate lots of random initial guesses and then
we calculate the alien states that result from
those random initial states and the idea is that
once we have those lem states we can proceed
to calculate the energy barrier between them
and so what you're seeing here is an animation
of one such energy barrier uh transition between
two vortex domain states and this energy barrier
can be used to calculate the relaxation time
which can then give us a blocking temperature
and if you recall this is the temperature
at which a magnetic signal is locked in
so in a 2017 study we examined thermal stability
and magnetite by calculating the energy barriers
in uniform grains of these equidimensional grains
and i've plotted these in red on the graph here
whereas i've added a line based purely on
a single domain theory in black so this is
a single domain theory it's extended well beyond
the region which in which grains can actually
support um just purely single domain structures
um so first we see that for small magnetic grains
um our models actually correspond quite well
with single domain theory as the size increases
we see the flowering of the domain structure
so this bowing out that i showed you before
and our results are beginning
to diverge they're becoming
much more stable with higher blocking
temperatures of a much larger grain
150 nanometers liquid dimensional
grains are surprisingly stable
much more than their single domain counterparts
would be if we were to extrapolate this uh black
line um but the second surprise is the presence
of this small unstable region which is also
um invisible to the single domain calculations
so you don't see this in the single domain model
and this unstable uh zone kind of appears in
other materials as well so uh this work done by um
miguel valdez grijalva uh al they examined the
temporal stability of greg i at room temperature
this was a function of grain size
and um a truncation factor of a cubot
the hedren so if you imagine a cubot
tehran it's basically two pyramids
that's stuck together and the truncation factor
is the amount of the corners that you slice off
and what we clearly see that there is a distinct
region where the relaxation times drop with the
blue square and they drop sharply as a function
of grain size of the truncated octahedra
but we can also note that just for octahedra the
unstable region is actually quite spread out it it
um it's um you know it doesn't
go up above 10 to the three
you know very very um unstable uh
very unstable geometry uh for greg eye
and finally for i
know the state region also although in
this case it's a little bit more difficult
um uh to see the blocking temperature on the graph
uh but if we uh examine these uh puliar curves of
these polar nomograms uh for the cubes um on the
right so for these is for these are for iron cubes
um of different sizes um as the functioning
relaxation time as a function of temperature
um we again see a behavior similar to magnetite so
the first curve so here uh 30 nanometers is a is a
flower something that's quite stable
we can see it's got a nice steep
polar curve the next curve is something from
the unstable region at 34 nanometers it's much
more shallow indicating something that's much
less thermally stable and then at 37 nanometers
again it's much more thermally stable um so can
we possibly speculate that grains like these
are responsible for the non-linear behavior
of the demagnetizing experiments in the lab
well the size ranges that we're talking about are
very very small uh you know so here in iron we're
looking at 30 to 37 uh previously you know
we're looking at something that's about what
10 20 nanometers in size not very big but
these are for equidimensional grains uh only
and we don't really know what's going
on uh with uh elongate grains um
and beyond that uh if we if we do start to
look at what happens uh when uh when our grains
uh become more elongate um we can map out all of
the possible domain structures and elongations
and um as you can imagine this is
actually quite a computational challenge
just as some of these numbers here show um
and even if we don't do anything clever uh
with the data that we have uh we still find some
really interesting things so what you're seeing
here is an animation of some lem state
so local energy minimum states of grains
as a function of elongation so this is uh quite
interesting because it diverges from our singleton
expectation uh we kind of imagine that as we
elongate the grain um we expect that these vortex
structures would lie along the axis along which we
um kind of stretch the grain but what we actually
see is that for quite a significant um elongation
up to until it kind of doubles its length
um the vortex collides uh perpendicular to the
axis of elongation um and the real question is
um what's um what's the what are the consequences
of this behavior for the thermal behavior
so in summary we've seen that our calculations
predict some very different behavior from
classical single domain theory and this
behavior is possibly the cause of why so
many of our measurements fail uh but in order to
map out an accurate picture of what's going on
really does require an enormous computational
effort and this is what i'm planning to do with
virgil which is a virtual paleomagnetic laboratory
so what we can do is make use of machine learning
parallel computing and to make some significant
progress to understand the magnetic recorders
that store valuable information about the early
formation of our planet and our solar system
and so i just thank you like
thank you very much for listening
thanks very much liz i think we
can all um uh raise our hands and
give liz a virtual round of applause
for um a really really interesting
uh a really interesting talk um so i will have
um plenty time for questions so if anybody has
a question please just raise your hand via zoom
or turn your camera on and wave frantically
and if nobody has a question i do have a ton of
questions less as always go for it oh i see that i
see witness put his hand up so um we'll we'll get
an inside question from from when to start with
number one yeah nice talk uh there's so i
guess one of the things i'd uh i think um
you know we've discussed before and it's
probably worth sharing with the community as well
is that um you know we've identified this
unstable zone you know in essence that's
just another sort of super paramagnetic region
yeah but the most interesting thing is something
you alluded to towards the end of the talk
there was this multiplicity of domain steps
you know normally we we associate multiplicity
of domain states with multi-domain grains
low remnants carriers i think what you've found
particularly in elongated grains are multiplicity
of domain states even for high remnants
extremely high remnants high stability grains
and um as a possible solution or a reason why we
get these non-repeatability of thermal cycling i
think it's this multiplicity of domain states as
we know multiplication must exist if you're going
to have non-repeatable ptrms and thermocycling
and they must be relatively high remnants carriers
and as you showed towards the end there in these
elongated grains a number of surprising things
you have uh the vortex cores along the hot axis
the hard shape axis which uh another thing that
might result in is uh inverse ams for instance
where you apply a field normal to the long axis
and actually uh the remnants changes on the
orthogonal axis for the magnetization changes
but the uh the availability of the main states
along the hard axis of the shape the hard and easy
elongation crystalline on the zotropi axis
at different temperatures they become more
or less favorable and as well as the easy long
axis all those multiplicative domain states and
the probability and the ability to switch between
one another and thermal cycling i think that is
uh the likely um region in which
which will answer yield answers for uh
ptm tails right yeah uh so um i
do have some slides uh if if um
so i i didn't include these at the end uh just
uh for fear that the torque would drag on um
but if um just a quick note on the energy barriers
here if we kind of consider energy so this this
energy barrier is something typical that we
will see in an elongate grain and what's uh
really cool about this is that you've
got a an asymmetric energy barrier
um the right energy barrier uh let's color those
in blue left energy barry let's color those in red
and the energy barrier um represents the
probability of something that's stable metastable
but takes some time to jump across and if you look
at the thermal behavior here so this is a plot of
um um i didn't put uh that's on the axis um
so basically you've got relaxation time log
of relaxation time on the y-axis and size for this
particular geometry here and you can see that the
um that the thermal behavior in equidimensional
grains is just one nice simple straight line um
and nice symmetric energy barriers that's what
you expect to see but in elongate grains it's
much more complicated and what this does is it
opens up the possibility of um like you say um
possible uh explanations for things like you
know fragile curvature or um um ptrm tails and
the reason why is because it everything depends on
in a thermal cycling experiment everything depends
on the thermal history so what as you as
you heat something up cool something down
the domain state that your assemblage of grains
is going to acquire depends on what the previous
uh the distribution of domain states were
and in this case you can see that there
are definitely inflection points and
points where the two possible thermal
behavior curves change as a function of of size
and you can easily imagine that if you built a
statistical model based on something like this
you would get a much more complicated um set of
thermal behavior from something that's just based
on this simple single domains theory so like you
say you you see these transitions from um so you
see here these transitions from e
uh from short axis to the long axis
and then you see transitions from uh for
higher temperatures you see transitions for
um the long axis to the short axis and then you
see transitions from short axis to short axis
and at certain temperatures and this is this
is the taker at certain temperatures certain
um domain transitions are more favorable than
others and that those probabilities have a
very important effect on what your thermal
cycling experiments are going to go what results
you're going to measure in the laboratory as as
you perform these thermal cycling experiments
thanks very much les and we have time for
some more questions if anyone has them
um so when you're looking at um the the um the
growing grain size is going up into multi-domain
uh particles i mean from a
pathogenic perspective as you said we
we're physically we are measuring the the stray
field of these particles um and i i forget what
paper you did and we had a graph showing the
increasing moment of the particles with grain size
for these very large multi-domain particles
what what is their sort of net moment
i know i guess many of the the main states
are are probably cancelling each other out
but um you know because of their large volume
any small bias could potentially be quite a large
moment um i don't i don't know the answer
to that i i did calculate them at some point
and um for the large grains they are relatively
small the remnants are really small because the
grains are very big and the domains aren't aren't
cooperating with each other as you would expect in
a multi-domain you know in a multi-domain grain
and it's going to be relatively small anyway um
so yeah i i i i can get you those numbers i i have
them somewhere i don't know exactly what they are
sorry oh that's fine i'd be curious to see them
yeah i can i can dig them out i've got them
so we have time for for uh another quick
question before we wrap it up for today
i don't know if i can make a comment
that's just what you just said
right by all means when so i mean i think the the
issue really with the multidomain grains is that
um you know as you form the main walls then the
effect of dislocations and impurities become more
important and if you're looking for estimates
of remnants in these grains that have well
established domain walls then and they're likely
to be affected by um defect densities and so forth
much more so than vortex structures i think uh
none of those uh well of course we have um we have
a strain energy in immoral but we don't actually
have a formal elastic problem in there to look at
defects so um those things i think still are
in the realm of the sort of analytic models
but i mean i wouldn't and also the the model that
les uh published in this paper from mike from nano
to micro or whatever it was called uh is highly
idealized it suggests uh if unless would like
disagree with me but it's just to show the type of
evolution from a vortex structure to a divine war
really rather than trying to be predictive in
any realistic sense of friends yeah and and i
mean we didn't um we certainly didn't try to do
any kind of thermal calculation you know those
those um those grains you can imagine um something
very slowly growing um but all you're really
doing is you're looking at the evil of the
possible a possible path of evolution for one
for one type of domain structure it's not you know
if if you wanted to do anything more complicated
then um yes you would have to include magnetic
restriction the model doesn't include that
i also have to you know look at these random
random initial guesses calculate what kinds
of possible domestics are available to you
probably a lot um the bigger the grains get
the more i mean i can just go back to one of those
early slides um you see like you know this this
thing here this thing um in in a relatively small
i i think these these kinds of things they're not
multi-domain they're not vortex what are they
they're kind of these weird these very weird
um domain structures and um they appear
in magnetite uh in grains that are around
sort of 500 nanometers volt volumetrically
so imagine a cube with a with an edge of
500 nanometers and about that size you'll get this
you just get this weird stuff um and uh the larger
sizes there are more um there are different
types of domain structure available to you
thanks very much les i think we'll have
one last question from uh shibuya-san
before we wrap up for tonight i thank you a very
interesting talk and i'm just curious that the
kind of hexagonal hexagonal uh domain structure
the actual uh magnetic direction uh through the
that kind of hexagon yeah up upward downward
about downward bound yeah yeah correct that's
it well it's it's it's kind of uh which which
one are you talking about are you talking about
this one this one this one yes yeah up up
down that's what they do that's right yes
they if there's a kind of a wave that goes
up down okay okay i'm just i i just thought
reading after your paper i just thought what the
what would be the domain structure very related
to the kind of uh very stable uh state so i i
found that that kind of domain structure and
that that is related to the uh directional domain
structure very core very close to core so even
the though that the smaller ones uh it would be
a little bit better to think about the way of the
main structure and which will make me to better
understanding of that what what we are looking at
yes um um i mean um you certain you certainly do
see this um kind of wave structure um i have a
slightly i think in the paper there's
a slightly better picture um and um
i mean what what's also interesting is that you
you you're uh switching between uh easy between
uh magneto crystal and easy easy directions as
you so as you transition as you as you correctly
um observe as you transition uh across the domain
wall yeah yeah it's very you kind of yeah yeah you
you kind of um see this yes that's it yeah but
always always in an easy direction so you're
always going to magnetic crystal an easy direction
then a different one then back up and down and up
and down yeah yeah so yes you definitely see that
um in in this grain um the the question about
whether it the whether it's the absolute lem
um is an astonishingly difficult question
because um the larger the grain um the
more lemon states that are available to you
uh finding a global finding any optimization
that involves finding the global minimum is
an extraordinarily um computationally challenging
problem the way that i um the way that we we can
kind of cheat in the smaller grains because we
just pick like i said you just pick 50 random
direction all the all the moments all randomized
and then you relax and statistically you should be
able to pick out what all of the possible lem
states are going to be in a very big grain um
even in an idealized version like this um
you can assume i think you can i think it's
safe to assume but it is just a hypothesis
um that the number of domain states will be
extremely large yeah and the reason
why you get here is because as has been
his observed previously is highly
constrained because each each um
solution is dependent on the previous solution
so it's it's like here it's like you're kind of
very slowly growing the grain it's analogous
to a process like that yeah yeah excellent
thank you very much less thank you for assigning
everybody for um for their their questions um we
have a little bit of time um uh afterwards uh
so just give want to um ask everybody to give
les another uh round of applause for um a
really uh exciting and interesting talk there
and i've even actually gone and got the right
title this time um so thank you very much les
so um just before everybody uh uh leaves they
just want to give you a quick reminder of our
upcoming schedule so the uk uh in just under uh
two weeks we're going we're changing um back to to
gmt so please keep an eye on the times local
times for yourself for when the next seminars are
and we've got three seminars left for the 2021
season before we break for uh christmas and
and the new year but we are looking for any
speakers um for our 22 2022 season so if anybody
is interested in giving a talk or know somebody
who uh might be interested in giving a talk please
and just get in touch and as a reminder we still
have our our youtube channel um where all of our
our recordings will go and this is where leslie's
talk will go a little bit later today or tomorrow
and so please uh subscribe if you don't want to
to miss out on any of our seminars and i just want
to thank everybody for joining magnets today
and we'll see you in a couple of weeks thanks